Stop, Mom!
妈 停下来！
Please, come back!
拜托你回来！
Why? Why are you leaving us?
为什么？为什么你要离开我们？
Ouch!
好痛
If you don't wake up soon,
要是不赶快起床的话
you will be late for school.
上学就要迟到了
Oh, no!
糟糕
Mita poured you a glass of milk.
三田小姐帮你倒牛奶了
What? You should have said so earlier!
什么？你应该早点说啊
You always make such a commotion every morning.
谁叫你每天早上都慌慌张张的
What are you doing, Kii? You're not a baby anymore.
希衣 你在干吗？ 你已经不是小婴儿了
She kept insisting to drink from that bottle.
她就一直坚持要用奶瓶喝呀
She wet her bed today, too.
昨晚还尿床了呢
What?
什么？
You can't do this, Kii.
希衣 你不能这样呀
You can't drink anything right before you sleep.
睡觉前不可以喝东西
Right. I'll teach you a trick that will stop you from wetting your bed.
对了 我教你一个不会尿床的秘诀
Let's go.
来啦
-Yui. When is Daddy coming home? -Yes?
-姐姐 爸比什么时候回来呀？ -怎么了？
What?
什么？
That's…
那个…
Didn't I tell you?
我没跟你说吗？
The four of us will live together from now on.
从今以后 我们四个要自己生活
So you need to become strong, Kii.
所以希衣要坚强起来
She's right.
没错
We're better off not having that man around!
我们最好不要跟那个男的一起生活
From now on, let's work together and do our best.
从现在起 我们一起努力生活吧
Let's get our spirits up!
加油！
Yui. The school I'm applying to will be having a parent-and-teacher meeting.
姐 我申请的学校要举办家长会
Oh, is that so?
这样啊？
Kaito. Why don't you give up applying to a private school?
海斗 你干吗不干脆放弃 申请私立学校啊？
What?
什么？
What are you trying to say?
我不懂你在说什么蠢话
Like I said, stop talking as if everyone is dumber than you!
我说过了 不要把别人当笨蛋
And like I said, stop hitting my head!
我也说过 别打我的头
Stop fighting first thing in the morning.
不要一大早就吵架
I have a question for everyone.
我有个问题要问大家
What?
什么？
What is it?
什么事？
From now on, whose order should I prioritize?
从现在起 我该优先听谁的指令？
Mr. Asuda's orders always came first,
之前都是以主人的指令优先
but I cannot get my priorities mixed up
如果每个人有不同的要求
if everyone has different requests.
我不能让优先次序乱掉
You could listen to me,
你可以听我的
-since I'm the eldest son. -What?
-因为我是长男 -什么啊？
Normally it should be Yui, since she's the eldest.
一般来说是姐吧 她是最大的
Shut up! You're just a kid!
你闭嘴啦 小屁孩
What's with your attitude? You're acting like a father!
你是怎样？一副爸爸的语气
Stop it, both of you.
就叫你们别吵了
Mita.
三田小姐
If we all have different requests, we will discuss among ourselves first.
我们意见不同时 会自己先讨论好
As you wish.
我知道了
Daddy has to be here, too!
爸比也要在这里才行
When a child does something wrong,
当小孩做错事时
it is a given that you reprimand them.
责备是应该的
It's something you should do…
这是你身为父亲
as a father.
应该做的事
Coming.
来了
-Yikes! It's the old hag next door! -Hey, wait!
-讨厌！是隔壁的老太婆 -喂 等等
I'm sorry about that!
不好意思
What do you need?
您有什么事？
I'm here to give you the circular notice!
我是来给你们传阅板的
I thought I should inform you about the neighborhood council meeting.
我想应该要通知你们社区会议的事
Is Mr. Asuda here?
阿须田先生在吗？
He has been absent from the meetings ever since his wife passed away.
太太去世之后 他就没参加过会议
I'm here to let him know that he has to attend this week.
我来是要跟他说 这星期一定要参加
Mr. Asuda has left.
主人已经离开了
What?
什么？
What do you mean?
你是什么意思？
Last night, Kii said that she will die if everyone doesn't live together.
昨晚 希衣说如果 大家不住一起 她就要自杀
There was a huge commotion.
造成了很大的骚动
The children are convinced that their father is at fault,
孩子们认为是爸爸的错
and persistently asked him if he really loved them.
然后逼问他是否爱他们
-Mr. Asuda… -That's enough!
-主人… -别说了
Then, it's just you guys living here now?
所以现在这个家只有你们吗？
Seriously.
真的假的？
What's going to happen if a fire breaks out again?
要是发生火灾了怎么办？
How troublesome.
麻烦死了
Don't worry. We won't cause any trouble for you.
不用担心 我们不会给你添麻烦的
Still, it's not normal for children to live with just their housekeeper.
但小孩只跟家政妇住还是很不正常
Seriously…
唉唷
Why am I living next to a family like this?
为什么我要跟这种家庭当邻居？
That old hag is going to spread rumors about us again.
那个老太婆一定又会到处散播谣言
No point worrying about it. Let's go, we're running late!
担心也没用 走吧 要迟到了
Have a safe trip.
路上小心
Mita.
三田小姐
Could you go kill that old hag?
你可以杀了那个老太婆吗？
As you wish.
我知道了
Wait!
等等！
It's just a joke! Oh…
我只是开玩笑的
Sorry.
抱歉
You're really weird, you know?
你真的很奇怪耶
You just agree to every request without any hesitation!
总是毫不迟疑地答应任何要求
As a housekeeper,
身为家政妇
shouldn't you talk more or at least smile?
你不该多说点话 至少也多笑点吗？
I heard that you think you shouldn't smile.
我听说你觉得自己不能笑
Just what happened to you?
你到底发生过什么事？
Try smiling now.
你笑笑看嘛
You do everything we ask, right?
我们说什么你都会做吧？
This is an order.
这是命令
I'm sorry,
我很抱歉
but I can't do that.
但我做不到
Why?
为什么？
If you insist that I do it,
要是你坚持要我这么做
I will quit.
我会辞职
Don't mind that.
那不用了
Have a safe trip.
路上小心
Hurry up!
快一点
Here!
看球
Hey!
喂！
Stop repeating the same mistakes!
不要一直犯相同的错啊
You guys are all slacking off!
你们太散漫了
All first-year students, do 100 push-ups!
一年级的 一百下俯卧撑
-Yes!
-是！
Hey, Kakeru.
喂 翔
Aren't you being too harsh?
你会不会太严厉了啊？
I just want everyone to do their best!
我只是想要每个人都全力以赴
Even so, you don't normally go overboard like this.
但你平常不会这么激动啊
Normally?
平常？
What's that? Are you saying I'm not normal?
什么意思？你是说我不正常吗？
Why are you so irritated?
你干吗那么暴躁？
I know you're enthusiastic since you just became the captain.
我知道你才刚当上队长 想好好表现
Don't take it out on us just because your dad left home.
别因为你爸离开家就迁怒我们
Wait, what?
喂 等等
How did you know that?
你怎么知道的？
That talkative hag lives next to you, remember?
你家隔壁住一个大嘴巴老太婆啊
This far is good enough.
到这里就可以了
I don't want my siblings to see us, anyway.
我不想被我的弟妹看到
-Got it. -Thank you so much for taking me home.
-好 -谢谢你特地送我回家
See you.
再见
Excuse me, Ozawa…
不好意思 学长
Hey!
奇怪
What are you doing here, Yui?
姐 你在做什么啊？
See you.
那再见了
Okay.
好
I'm sorry to interrupt while you're busy.
抱歉打扰啦
Hey, stop that!
喂 闭嘴啦
That's my line! What are you doing here?
你才是 在这里干什么？
He just took me home. That's all.
他只是送我回家而已
-Is that wrong? -All of you are the same!
-有问题吗？ -你们都一个样
When you turn at the tree
在树的地方转弯
And walk further
然后继续前进
Welcome home.
欢迎回家
We're home.
我们回来了
Mita!
三田小姐
Yes.
是
Could you go complain to the old hag next door?
你可以去骂骂隔壁的老太婆吗？
She has been talking bad about us.
她在我们背后说闲话
As you wish.
我知道了
Wait. Stop that, Mita.
等等 三田小姐 别去
Hey!
喂！
Just take Kii home.
先带希衣进屋吧
As you wish.
我知道了
Kii.
希衣
Why did you stop her, Yui?
姐 你干吗阻止她？
If you do that, things are just going to get complicated.
要是这么做 事情只会变得更复杂
What is it?
你们在干吗？
Do you need anything with me?
有事吗？
No, it's nothing.
没有 没事
Ms. Minagawa. Could you stop talking about unnecessary things to others?
阿姨 可以请你别再 说我们的闲话了吗？
Like how our father left home.
像是我爸离开家之类的
Could you not make false accusations?
可以不要乱说吗？
Also, isn't it true that your father left home?
还有你爸离家不是事实吗？
Did he perhaps have a mistress?
他该不会有小三吧？
Or did your mother know about it?
你们的妈妈知道吗？
You see,
我呀
I sympathize with you kids.
很同情你们呢
First, your mother died,
先是妈妈去世
and now your father abandoned you.
然后爸爸又抛弃你们
How pitiful.
好可怜呀
Let's go, Tsubasa.
小翼 走吧
-You'll be late for your violin lessons. -Okay.
-小提琴课要迟到了 -好
Wait!
等一下
We weren't abandoned.
我们才不是被抛弃
Stop it already. Sorry to cause you trouble.
别说了 抱歉给您添麻烦了
Why are you apologizing?
你干吗道歉？
Your husband is having an affair too, right?
你老公不是也在搞外遇吗？
Your kid said it.
你家小孩说的
What are you saying?
你在乱说什么啊？
Let's go.
我们走
Hey!
喂！
Would you stop causing trouble already?
你可以别再惹事了吗？
Things are already troublesome as it is!
事情已经很棘手了
Then, stop flirting around!
那你就不要在附近卿卿我我啊
You even bragged to Dad that you're going to take care of us!
你还跟爸夸下海口 说要照顾我们
Oh, thanks.
谢谢
I'm telling you not to do anything that will cause trouble for the family!
我是叫你别再替家里找麻烦了
Then, are you fine letting that old hag spout all those nonsense?
就算那个老太婆乱说话 你也无所谓吗？
Seriously, you guys are so annoying!
烦死了
If you want to fight, do it outside!
要吵去外面吵啦
You listen, too. It involves the whole family.
你也要听 这跟我们家有关
Sorry, but I have cram school.
抱歉 我要去补习了
I'm counting on you for the parent-and-teacher meeting, Yui.
姐 家长会就拜托你了
Didn't I tell you not to attend a private school?
我不是叫你别上私立学校吗？
-Hey, Yui. -Yes?
-姐姐 -怎么了？
What's a family breakdown?
什么是“家庭破碎”？
What?
什么？
Why are you asking that, Kii?
你怎么会问这个呢 希衣？
Tsubasa told me that.
小翼跟我说
"You're having a family breakdown now, Kii."
“希衣 你的家庭破碎了”
Oh…
这…
That means…
意思是…
A family that has issues and flaws
家庭因为有问题或缺失
turns into a complete mess,
所以变得分崩离析
and those who have not experienced it sympathizes and pities you.
而家庭完好的人会同情、可怜你
That's what a "family breakdown" means.
这就是所谓的“家庭破碎”
Mita, go kill them all together with that hag!
三田小姐 去把老太婆全家都杀掉
As you wish.
我知道了
You don't have to go, Mita!
三田小姐 你不用去
Mita.
三田小姐
Could you prioritize my orders from now on?
从现在开始 可以请你 优先听我的指令吗？
Understood.
我知道了
Seriously…
真是的
What the heck!
什么跟什么！
You won't have a family breakdown, Ku.
酷宝 你的家庭没有破碎
What should I do, Mita?
三田小姐 我该怎么办？
There's the neighborhood council meeting, and the parent-and-teacher meeting.
又是社区会议 又是家长会
That is something you should decide for yourself.
那是你自己要决定的事情
That again?
又是这一句？
Just tell me what you think.
你就告诉我你在想什么嘛
You must have your own thoughts.
你一定也有自己的想法
I'm not thinking of anything.
我什么都没想
You can always reach me through my phone.
你们可以随时打我的手机
Thank you very much!
非常感谢你们
-The house was nice, wasn't it? -Yes.
-房子很棒嘛 对吧？ -真的不错
Chief.
课长
Oh, Natori. What's up?
名取啊 怎么了？
You seem popular with housewives.
你好像很受主妇的欢迎嘛
Aren't you more suitable to work here?
你是不是更适合在这里工作呀？
-Right? -Yes.
-对吧？ -是
-You think so? -Well then.
-是这样吗？ -那么
Do your best to sell more houses.
你就努力卖更多房子吧
We'll continue to make good ones too.
我们也会努力盖好房子的
MIE KAZAMA
（风间美枝）
The number you have reached is not available.
您拨的电话是空号
Where are you staying now?
你现在住在哪里啊？
Well…
嗯
At a business hotel near my company.
公司附近的商务旅馆
Then, what will you do about Yui and the kids?
那结和孩子们你打算怎么办？
This can't go on forever.
也不能一直这样下去
I know I have to do something.
我也知道
Sorry to keep you waiting.
抱歉让您久等了
Please excuse me.
不好意思
Let's eat first!
总之先吃饭吧
It looks so good.
看起来好好吃
-Here you go. -Thanks.
-来 给你 -谢谢
I'm digging in!
我开动了
Yuck, again!
又来了
-What's wrong? -Well…
怎么了？
This always happens.
每次都这样
Even if I order the same thing as someone else,
只要我跟别人点一样的餐
mine always has insects in it.
我的餐总是会有虫
-Excuse me. -Yes?
-不好意思 -是
There's an insect in her food.
食物里面有虫
Just how do you do things here?
你们是怎么做事的？
I'm really sorry!
真的很对不起
I will have it changed right away.
我马上帮您换一份新的
Seriously…
搞什么啊？
Right…
对了
So what did you want to talk about?
你找我想说什么？
When Kii asked if you love her,
在希衣问你爱不爱她时
why did you give her that answer?
你为什么那样回答她？
I don't know.
我不知道
What's with that answer?
你在说什么啊？
You could have just said that you love her!
你应该要直接说你爱她啊
That's true, but…
话是这么说 但是…
If I hadn't married Nagiko
要是我没有跟凪子结婚
or didn't have children,
或是没有小孩
I couldn't help but think
我忍不住一直去想
-It's good, Daddy! -Really?
-爸比 好好吃喔 -真的吗？
When I hit Kii that day,
在我打希衣的那天
Mita told me that it's a given to reprimand children
三田小姐跟我说 小孩如果做错事
if they did something wrong.
惩罚他们是天经地义的事
But I don't have the confidence
但我打从心底
to tell them that I love them
实在没有自信说出
from the bottom of my heart.
我爱他们
Well… You're being too honest, Keiichi.
姐夫 你太诚实了啦
Don't all fathers lie and pretend?
爸爸不都会说谎 假装一下吗？
I wish that your father would teach me, Urara.
我真希望你爸会教我怎么做
What should I do to nurture parental love?
我该怎么做才能培养父爱呢？
What's that?
这是在干吗？
Dad!
爸！
Didn't I tell you not to come since I'll do something about this?
我不是说我会处理 叫你不要来吗？
Shut up.
吵死了
Nothing will turn out well if I leave it to you.
要是交给你 绝对不会有好下场的
I've had enough of your nonsense!
我已经受够你的胡说八道了
Here.
这里
Hurry up and sign this.
快签了这个
An adoption application form?
收养文件？
-Wait, Dad! -Stay out of this!
-爸 等等 -你给我闭嘴
Listen.
你听好了
Yui can choose to be adopted on her own will,
结可以自己选择要不要被收养
but the other three will need the father's consent
但其他三个小孩需要生父的许可
to be adopted by someone else.
才可以被别人收养
Wait, but…
等等 但…
Thanks for waiting. Here is your gratin.
久等了 这是您的焗饭
We don't need that! Get lost!
我们不需要这个 快滚！
Stop shouting!
不要大吼大叫啦
Hurry up.
快一点
You don't love those kids, right?
反正你也不爱那些孩子吧？
I'm sorry,
抱歉
This is too sudden.
这太突然了
He's right, Dad.
对啊 爸
Shut up!
吵死了！
To those kids,
对那些孩子来说
every single second matters.
现在每分每秒都很重要
Do you even understand that?
你到底懂不懂？
I…
我…
I'm sorry!
对不起
Wait, Keiichi!
姐夫 等等
Are you running away, you coward?
懦夫 你要逃走吗？
Wait!
站住！
Dad! Are you all right?
爸 你还好吗？
I'm sorry, Urara!
小丽 抱歉
Well, shall we start with running?
那么开始跑步吧
Hey.
喂
What are you guys doing?
你们在干吗啊？
We can't follow you anymore.
我们没办法再听你的了
What? What are you talking about?
什么？你在说什么？
Could you resign as the captain?
你可以辞掉队长一职吗？
Hey. Are you kidding me?
喂 你在开玩笑吗？
Say something, the rest of you!
你们说点什么啊
Do whatever you want.
随便你们
I would rather quit a club like this!
这种社团 我退出也罢
MONEY CHANGER
（兑币机）
We did it! You actually got it!
太好了！你抓到了
Let's play one more time!
再玩一次
You're really good! Let's try it again.
你好厉害 我们再玩一次
What the hell is wrong with this?
这是怎样啊？
Hey!
喂！
-What are you doing? -Quit bugging me!
-你在干什么？ -不要烦我
Hey!
喂！
Hey! Let go of me!
喂 放开我！
Are you the eldest son?
你是长男吗？
Any younger siblings?
有弟弟妹妹吗？
You're so young, and you're already invoking your right to remain silent?
这么年轻就会行使沉默权了吗？
Excuse me…
不好意思
I'm Kakeru Asuda's father.
我是阿须田翔的父亲
I told him to contact a guardian,
我叫你儿子打给监护人
but your son called the housekeeper instead.
但他却打给了家政妇
So I told him he can't leave.
所以我不让他离开
I'm sorry.
我很抱歉
Well, the arcade employees want to settle this amicably, too.
游乐场的店员也不想把事情闹大
Could you give him a stern warning?
你可以用父亲的身份 严正警告他吗？
No point telling him that.
跟他讲没有意义
That man is not a father to me.
那个男人不是我的爸爸
Hey, Kakeru!
喂 翔
Sorry. I'll talk some sense into him.
抱歉 我会好好管教他
-I'm really sorry about this. -It's all right.
-真的很不好意思 -没关系
Hey, Kakeru.
翔
I'm sorry.
对不起
It's all because of me.
都是因为我的关系
That's not what happened!
事情才不是这样
Hey, what are you doing?
喂 你在干吗啊？
What?
怎么了？
I…
我…
I'm quitting basketball.
不打篮球了
What?
什么？
But I thought you loved it.
我以为你很爱篮球
Who cares about that?
很重要吗？
Forget that. Can I have a cigarette?
别说了 可以给我烟吗？
What are you saying?
你在说些什么？
Then, I'll buy it myself.
不然我就自己买
Give me your card.
你的卡拿来
Don't be ridiculous. You're a minor.
别胡闹了 你还未成年
Then tell me!
那你跟我说啊
Why can't a minor smoke?
为什么未成年不能吸烟？
What?
什么？
Well, you see…
这个嘛…
That's because…
那是因为…
Smoking as a minor
未成年吸烟
interferes with your growth and it deteriorates your brain.
会阻碍发育以及伤害脑部
It only helps raise weak and immature humans
抽烟只是脆弱不成熟的人
who pretend to be full-fledged adults.
装作自己能独当一面的方法而已
She's right.
没错
Isn't it fine?
这样不是很好吗？
I'm stupid in the first place.
我本来就很笨
Why would someone like you care how I turn out to be?
你这种人为什么要关心 我会变成什么样？
"Someone like you"?
“我这种人”？
What?
怎么？
You want me to call you "Dad"?
你还想要我叫你“爸”吗？
Seriously.
笑死人了
Why did Mom fall in love with someone like you?
妈为什么会爱上你这种人？
If she hadn't married you,
要是她没跟你结婚
she would have had a happy life!
一定会过得很幸福的
Hey.
喂
Seriously…
真是的
Mita.
三田小姐
Sorry to trouble you,
抱歉给你添麻烦了
but please take care of him.
但请你照顾他
-About what? -What?
-有关什么？ -什么？
Oh, I mean…
我的意思是
The various aspects of the children's lives.
孩子们生活的各个层面
What do you mean by "various"?
“各个层面”是什么意思？
Well, that's…
就是…
Please contact me if anything happens again.
要是又有事情发生 请跟我联络
As you wish.
我知道了
Kakeru.
翔
Mita.
三田小姐
How did it go with the police?
警察怎么说？
They agreed to let him go,
在主人会管教他的情况下
What's the meaning of this, Kakeru?
翔 你到底在搞什么？
Everyone was worried!
大家都很担心你
Shut up!
吵死了
It wasn't my fault!
又不是我的错
Hey, Kakeru!
喂 翔
What are you doing?
你在干吗？
Why not?
又不会怎样
It's a waste to throw it away.
反正丢掉也是浪费
-Just stop this already! -Let go!
-你够了没？ -放手
Hey, Kakeru!
喂 翔
I said, let go!
我叫你放手
Seriously… What are you doing?
唉唷 你在干什么啊？
You guys will never understand…
我的心情…
how I feel right now.
你们永远不会懂的
Kakeru!
翔！
I can't forgive my father,
我无法原谅我爸
but I think my siblings still need someone like him around.
但我觉得我的弟弟妹妹需要他
I just don't know what to do.
我不知道该怎么办
My head is in a mess now.
我现在脑子一片混乱
Then,
那么
let's give it a good thought together after school today.
今天放学后 我们一起想办法吧
Ozawa.
学长
Do you really love me?
你真的爱我吗？
What are you saying?
你在说什么啊？
Of course, I do.
我当然爱你啊
Then, what do you like about me?
那你喜欢我什么？
What?
什么？
Ozawa.
学长
You just accept me
你会跟我在一起
because you can kiss me and stuff, right?
只是因为可以接吻之类的吧？
When the person I love is in pain, I want to be by his side.
如果我爱的人很痛苦 我会想陪在他身边
I want to do my best to help him.
尽我所能地帮助他
I think this is what it means to be in a relationship.
我想这才是在一起的意义
What are you trying to say?
你到底想说什么？
I know that things have been tough since your mom passed away,
我知道你妈去世后 你很辛苦
but you've never listened to what I had to say either.
但我说什么你都没在听
Like where we should travel,
像是我们该去哪里旅游
or about my dreams and my future.
或是我的梦想和未来
Are we even in a relationship right now?
我们现在还算是在交往吗？
I'm sorry that I didn't understand your feelings!
对不起 我都不懂你的感受
Forget about it.
算了吧
I'll go to your house.
我会去你家
So don't be mad at me.
拜托你别生我的气了
What?
干吗？
Will you nag at me for skipping school?
你是要念我翘课吗？
No.
不是
I'm just wondering if you need me to do anything.
我只是在想你需不需要我做任何事
Then…
那…
Play one round with me.
跟我玩一场
As you wish.
我知道了
One more time.
再一场
-One more time! -As you wish.
-再一场 -我知道了
That's enough.
够了
If there is nothing else,
要是没有别的事
I will resume cleaning.
我就继续打扫了
Wait.
等一下
You'll really do anything I ask, right?
我说什么你都会做 对吧？
If it is within my means.
只要我做得到的话
Then…
那么…
Let me do you.
让我上你
There's no one around.
反正现在也没人
It's fine, right?
没关系吧？
What?
怎么？
So I guess you can't do things like this.
我猜你做不到这种事吧？
As you wish.
我知道了
What?
什么？
What should I start with?
我该从哪里开始？
Should I kiss you?
我应该要亲你吗？
Or should I take off my clothes first?
还是我要先脱掉衣服？
Then…
那…
Take off your clothes.
把衣服脱掉
Understood.
我知道了
-Stop! -What are you doing?
-住手 -你们在干什么？
Mita?
三田小姐
What's the meaning of this?
这究竟是怎么回事？
Kakeru asked to let him do me.
翔要求说要上我
So I asked
所以我就问
if I should kiss him or take off my clothes.
我要先亲他还是先脱衣服
He told me to take off my clothes.
他叫我先脱衣服
Wear your clothes now.
你快穿上衣服
As you wish.
我知道了
Did you really ask her to do that?
你真的叫她这么做吗？
Kakeru?
翔？
Why can't I?
为什么不行？
Just what are you thinking?
你到底在想什么？
Stop messing around with me!
不要再来烦我了
You're not even doing anything for the family!
你根本也没有为家里做任何事
Hey! What the hell is wrong with you?
喂 你到底想怎么样？
You've got to be kidding me!
在开什么玩笑？
What are you doing, Kakeru?
你干什么啊 翔？
Stop putting all the blame on me.
别把错全推到我身上
This home turned into such a mess
这个家会变成这样
And because Mom killed herself!
还有妈自杀害的
Say, Mita…
三田小姐
What would have happened if I hadn't appeared on time?
要是我没有及时出现 会发生什么事？
Did you
你真的…
really intend to do that with Kakeru?
打算跟翔那么做吗？
Yes.
是
Jeez…
天啊
What's wrong with this house?
这个家到底怎么回事？
I'll be home late today, Mita.
三田小姐 我今天会晚点回家
I might be staying overnight elsewhere.
可能会在外面过夜
Understood.
我知道了
-Were you waiting for me, Chief? -Well…
-课长 你是在等我吗？ -我…
Sorry.
抱歉
I just really wanted to talk to you.
我无论如何都想跟你说话
-Please don't act like a stalker! -No…
-请不要像个跟踪狂一样 -不
I know that something is wrong with me, too.
我也知道我这样不好
But I just don't know what I should do anymore.
但我真的不知道该怎么办
I can't go home,
我回不了家
and I have no one to confide in.
也没有人能倾诉
You're the only one
你是唯一
who understands me.
了解我的人
Didn't you tell me
你不是跟我说过
that I don't have to force myself to act like a good person?
我不用逼自己装成好人的样子吗？
You said I could be myself.
你说过我可以做自己
It's the first time someone ever said that to me.
这是第一次有人跟我这么说
It's also my first time to be so deeply in love with someone.
这也是我第一次这么爱一个人
I see.
不会吧？
So that's how it is.
原来是这样啊
Why are you here?
你为什么在这里？
Don't tell me…
你该不会…
You're going out with him?
跟他在一起了吧？
I didn't want to say this,
我不想这么说
but it was tough on me, too.
但是我也很痛苦
Will you give up on me now?
你可以放弃我了吗？
Hey.
喂
What are you doing?
你在干什么啊？
You keep staring at someone else's house.
一直盯着别人家看
I hope you're not planning anything strange.
该不会想做什么奇怪的事吧？
That's not it!
才不是这样
Wow, so scary.
天啊 好恐怖
You can't follow people like him, Tsubasa.
你不可以学这种人喔 小翼
Okay.
好
That damn old hag.
那个死老太婆
What is it?
做什么？
My work for today is done,
我今天的工作已完成
so I will excuse myself.
恕我失陪了
Mita!
三田小姐
I have a request.
我有个请求
Could you turn this house upside down?
你可以把这个家搞得天翻地覆吗？
Is that…
那是…
an order?
命令吗？
Of course.
当然
As you wish.
我知道了
So what should I do?
那我该怎么做？
You could tear down the building!
你可以拆了这栋建筑
I will require a bulldozer for that.
那样我需要一台堆土机
Then,
那…
blow it apart with dynamite!
用炸弹炸掉
Where do I get something like that?
我应该去哪里找炸弹？
Then…
不然…
Let's see…
那就…
Damn it.
该死
What should I do?
我该怎么做？
What?
怎么？
You must think I'm hopeless, right?
你一定觉得我没救了吧？
Here I am struggling with all my worries,
我在这边烦恼
Do you even understand how I'm feeling?
你到底懂不懂我的感受啊？
I understand.
我懂
What?
什么？
Hey!
喂！
What are you doing?
你在干什么？
Wait, what are you writing?
等等 你在写什么？
Hey. What did you mean when you said you understand my feelings?
喂 你说你懂我的心情是什么意思？
I WANT TO PROTECT MY FAMILY
（我想要守护我的家庭）
Why…
为什么…
FAMILY
（家庭）
I WANT TO PROTECT
（我想要守护）
Hey.
喂
What are the both of you up to?
你们两个想做什么？
I WANT TO PROTECT MY FAMILY
（我想要守护我的家庭）
I'm sorry that I'm late.
抱歉我来晚了
Haven't I asked you to help, sir?
先生 我不是跟你说过了吗？
I'm sure I told you to warn your son.
我叫你好好管教儿子
Oh, I'm sorry.
我很抱歉
When I asked the housekeeper, she said it was an order by your son.
我问了家政妇后 她说是你儿子命令她做的
Just what's wrong with your family?
你家到底怎么回事啊？
Oh, that's…
这个…
How should I explain this…
该怎么说呢…
Everything is wrong with this family.
这个家问题可多了
The father is never home,
爸爸从不回家
the housekeeper is unpredictable,
家政妇捉摸不定
the eldest daughter isn't home at this hour,
长女这个时间了还不回家
and the eldest son is a delinquent.
长男还是个不良少年
I'm so scared that I can't fall asleep at night.
我每晚都害怕到睡不着觉
Why don't you reflect on yourself?
你为什么不反省一下啊？
Your late wife in heaven must be crying now.
你过世的太太现在一定在天上哭
Hey. Don't just say anything you want here!
喂 你不要乱说话喔
You were spreading rumors about our family!
你到处散播我们家的谣言
What's with that attitude?
你那是什么态度啊？
You're not even apologizing for your wrongdoings.
自己做错事了还不道歉
If that's how you will act, I'm going to file a victim report.
你要是这种态度 那我就要报案了
Calm down, ma'am.
冷静一点 太太
You're neighbors,
都是邻居
and he's just a minor.
而且他还未成年
-Just talk things through. -Why should I do that?
-把事情讲开就好嘛 -我为什么要这么做？
Boys like him deserve to be arrested.
这种小孩就应该要逮捕
It will be safer here without him.
这附近才会安全
Please take him to the police station now.
请快点把他带去警察局
Well then, stand up.
好吧 起立吧
Come on, stand up.
快点起来
Let's go.
走吧
Come.
起来
Excuse me…
抱歉
What?
想怎样？
-You have a complaint? -No, well…
-你还想抱怨啊？ -不 那个…
I'm truly sorry!
我真的很抱歉
It's all my fault. You can blame everything on me.
都是我的错 你可以都怪在我头上
I beg you!
我求你了
But just one thing.
但只有一件事
Kakeru is not a delinquent.
翔不是不良少年
As the eldest son,
他身为长男
he's doing his best for everyone.
总是努力为大家付出
Ever since their mother died,
自从他妈妈去世后
he's been trying his best for this family.
他一直都很努力支撑家庭
His father is hopeless,
是我这个爸爸很没用
so he wants to protect this family more than anyone else!
所以他比谁都想守护这个家
My late wife told me this.
我的太太曾跟我说
"If I caught a cold,
“要是我感冒了
all the kids would be sleeping."
即使所有的小孩都睡了”
"But Kakeru would be awake the entire night to change my wet towel
“翔还是会整晚 不眠不休地帮我换湿毛巾
and wipe away my sweat."
还会帮我擦汗”
Kakeru is actually a really nice boy.
翔真的是一个善解人意的男生
He worries about this family,
他总是为这个家操心
and hopes for everyone to be happy,
希望大家都快乐
unlike me!
不像我
I will take responsibility and clean your walls.
我会负责清理你家的围墙
So please forgive him.
所以拜托你原谅他
I beg you!
我求你了
Aren't you glad, Daddy?
爸爸 真是太好了
They'll forgive him as long as we clean the walls.
只要我们把围墙清干净 他们就会原谅我们
Right.
对啊
But…
但是…
this won't come off without special detergent, right?
这个不用特殊的清洁剂擦不掉吧？
I have it.
我有
All right. Let's do this.
好 来擦吧
I'll help, too!
我也来帮忙
Okay.
好
Thanks.
谢谢你
I'm supposed to be studying now, you know…
你也知道 我该读书了
I…
我…
Mom once told me…
妈曾跟我说
"Our family will be fine
“只要有翔在
as long as you're here, Kakeru."
我们家一定没问题的”
But…
但是…
I don't have the confidence to meet Mom's expectations.
我没有自信能达到妈的期望
I want to do something for everyone,
我想为大家做些什么
but I have no idea what I should do.
但是我完全不知道该怎么做
I just know that I have to do something.
我只知道我要做点什么
I grew more and more anxious,
我越来越焦虑
and things just wouldn't go well.
然后事情就越来越糟
Kakeru.
翔
I will protect you.
我来守护你
Man…
真是的
You ruined the moment.
你破坏了这个气氛
Mita.
三田小姐
Can you make us some midnight snacks after this?
弄完这个之后 你可以帮我们煮宵夜吗？
I can.
可以
Well then, let's eat.
那么开动吧
Thank you for the food.
我开动了
So good.
好好吃
Aren't you hungry, Kii?
希衣 你不饿吗？
I'll wet my bed if I eat right before sleeping.
我怕我吃了会尿床
You shouldn't worry about it.
你不用担心啦
Kakeru wet his bed until third grade.
翔尿床尿到三年级
You didn't have to say that, Dad…
这种事就不用说了 爸…
Kaito.
海斗
If you don't mind, can I attend the teacher-and-parent meeting?
要是你不介意 我可以参加家长会吗？
I'm fine with it.
我都可以
Mita.
三田小姐
Could you also let Yui know
可以请你跟结说
that I'll attend the neighborhood council meeting?
我会参加社区会议吗？
I believe you should tell her that yourself.
我认为你应该亲自跟她说
What?
什么？
Why are you eating ramen here?
你为什么在这里吃拉面？
Oh, well…
这个…
Who said you can come home?
谁说你可以回家的？
You've got it wrong, Yui.
姐 不是啦
Some things happened.
发生了很多事情
And what is that?
发生什么事？
The thing is…
就是…
-Because of me-- -It's all right, Kakeru.
-都是我的错 -翔 没关系
But…
但是…
Yui.
结
I'll go home.
我要走了
Oh, right.
对了
Daddy's stone!
爸比的石头
Right.
对
Mita found it.
三田小姐找到的
This stone…
这个…
Can I keep it for now?
可以先让我留着吗？
I want to put it back into that box one day.
总有一天 我想再放回那个盒子里
Sure.
好啊
Thanks.
谢谢你
See you.
那我走了
Yes?
谁？
Oh, Mita.
三田小姐
I brought you your washed clothes.
你的衣服洗好了
These…
这些…
You picked them up for me?
是你帮我捡起来的吗？
If there is nothing else,
要是没有别的事
I will excuse myself.
恕我失陪了
Mita!
三田小姐
I'm sorry about everything.
最近真的很对不起
Also…
还有…
Thank you.
谢谢你
I believe…
我认为
That is something you should tell your father.
你应该要跟你爸爸说
Also…
还有…
What?
什么？
This is the invoice for my overtime hours today.
这是今天加班的收据
TO: MR. KEIICHI ASUDA OVERTIME PAYMENT
（阿须田惠一先生收 加班费用）
Please excuse me.
我先失陪了
I'm sorry, everyone!
大家 对不起
Will you guys allow me to play basketball with everyone again?
你们可以让我再跟你们一起打球吗？
I don't care even if you make me run errands!
我什么事都愿意做
Please! I beg you!
拜托大家了
HARUMI HOUSEKEEPING AGENCY
（晴海家政妇介绍所）
This is the referral commission for this month.
这是这个月的介绍费
Sorry to make you do this all the time.
一直以来都不好意思呢
Thanks.
谢谢你
I will excuse myself now.
那么我先失陪了
Oh, one minute.
等一下
Here's some monaka.
最中饼
They're delicious. It's sweet, so have some.
很甜很好吃喔 你拿一点吧
OGURA MONAKA
（小仓最中）
No, I'm fine.
不 不用了
You know…
那个啊
I heard that the eldest son in that family
我听说那个家的长男
is a handful to deal with.
不太好处理呢
No, not really.
不 没什么问题
But you know,
但是你知道吗？
boys like him are just my cup of tea.
那种男生是我喜欢的类型
I just love boys like him!
我最喜欢他那种男生了
Wait…
等等
If I recall, your son would be the same age as him
我记得没错的话 要是你儿子还活着
if he were still alive.
应该跟他同岁喔
Me and my mouth. Maybe I said something unnecessary again.
我的嘴巴 我好像说了不该说的话
Please excuse me.
恕我失陪了
Share the cola with Mom.
跟妈妈分可乐吧
-Okay! -Here.
-好！ -来吧
Is it good?
好喝吗？
Yes, it's good.
好喝
-You're such a baby. -Right.
-果然是小朋友呢 -对呀
Just tell him that you'll be adopted by me!
去告诉他我要收养你们！
Are you guys going to forgive that man?
难道你们打算原谅那个男人吗？
Just leave me alone!
别再烦我了
What should we do?
我们该怎么办啊？
I am not stating my opinion about your family matters.
我绝不会对你们的家事发表意见
She might have been trying to kill herself.
她可能会想结束自己的生命
Mita.
三田小姐
Kill me.
杀了我吧
As you wish.
我知道了
Just ignore me even if I tell you to stop.
就算我叫你停下来 你也不要理我
Wait….
等等…
Please, stop it!
拜托你了 快住手
Subtitle translation by: Qianni Lu
字幕翻译：吴敬美